<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Famous conference between Pope Clement the Xth and Cardinal de Monte Alto concerning the late discovery of the Masse in Holy Scripture made by the worthy Father Patrick, an excellent engineer of the Church of Rome in England</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40846</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F368</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7044</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12801811</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12801811</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94068</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40846)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94068)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 379:36)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Famous conference between Pope Clement the Xth and Cardinal de Monte Alto concerning the late discovery of the Masse in Holy Scripture made by the worthy Father Patrick, an excellent engineer of the Church of Rome in England</title>
                  <author>Clement X, Pope, 1590-1676.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 30, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.R. and N.T. for Moses Pitt ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A satire.</note>
                  <note>Errata on p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mass --  Anecdotes</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94068:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A FAMOUS CONFERENCE BETWEEN POPE <hi>CLEMENT</hi> the X<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> AND CARDINAL <hi>de Monte Alto,</hi> Concerning the late Diſcovery of the MASSE IN Holy Scripture, MADE By the Worthy Father <hi>Patrick,</hi> An Excellent Engineer of the <hi>CHURCH</hi> of <hi>ROME</hi> in <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Latet anguis in herba.</l>
               <l>Ridendo dicere verum quis Vetat.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. R.</hi> and <hi>N. T.</hi> for <hi>Moſes Pitt</hi> at the <hi>Angell</hi> in St: <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1674.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:94068:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94068:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honeſt Reader:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>FAther PATRICK the Popes known Agent in <hi>England,</hi> and the reſt of his Diſguiſed Brethren ſtudy Night and Day how to cheat poor Souls into a Belief and Profeſsion of that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion that is deſtructive to the good of both Body and Soul: Subtilty and Fraud as you may perceive in this Conference are not wanting to this good Father in the proſecution of this evill Deſigne. His Looks, Carriage, and Speech proclaime him to be a Saint: I doubt not but ſome upon whom he hath prevailed to deny their Religion, and their God, Judg him to be no leſs: But that their mistakes may better appear to our World, and that none may be deceived with his fair Face, and Countenance, nor with that ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
<pb facs="tcp:94068:3"/> Affirmation, <hi>That the Maſs is to be found in Holy Scripture,</hi> of which the Papists make great uſe. This ſhort Conference which preſents you with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but that which may be proved if Queſtioned, hath been Written by a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Friend of the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94068:3"/>
            <head>A CONFERENCE Between a Noted CARDINAL of ROME, And the Preſent POPE, <hi>CLEMENT</hi> the X: About a New Diſcovery of the Popiſh MASS in Holy Writt.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Holy Father,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou'l pardon my Curioſity that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to know wherefore there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears upon your Pontificall Face ſuch extraordinary Expreſſions of joy. His Holineſs returned to the worthy Cardinall this anſwer; If my Face bears ſome teſtimonies of my Inward ſatisfaction and joy, I have juſt cauſe for it, for I have even now learnt a Diſcovery that hath been made in my time that will render my Reign moſt famous to all Poſterity.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:94068:4"/>
            <p> Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the <hi>6th:</hi> was over-joyed to ſee that in his dayes ſuch a naked and an excellent part of the World as is <hi>America,</hi> was found out; I have far more reaſon to rejoyce becauſe that in my days things of greater concernment that relate to Heaven and Happineſs have been ſearcht out, and happily diſcovrred; the Holy Maſs is found to be hid in a corner of holy Scripture. The Maſs in holy Scripture! quoth the Cardinall full of admiration, how can that be? I know not how many have been enquiring for it there, and have turned over every page to ſee whether they could ſpy any appearance of it in that place, and as <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>badiah</hi> ſaid to <hi>Elijah</hi> concerning <hi>Ahab,</hi> There is no Nation or Kingdom (whither my Lord hath not ſent to ſeek thee, and when they ſaid he is not there, he took an Oath of the Kingdom and Nation that they found thee not; thus as I may ſay our holy men have dealt with the Scripture, and the Maſs; there is ſcarce a page or a Verſe that hath been diligently examin'd and enquired into, and when our Holy and Religious Brethren have ſeen no ſhape of the Maſs in Scripture themſelves, they have as it were taken an Oath from the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Evangeliſts that they found it not: but all their ſtudy &amp; enquiry hath been hitherto to ſo little purpoſe, ſo that they have at laſt freely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:94068:4"/> that the Maſs is only to be found in our Old ſtorehouſe of rotten Traditions: It maybe that theſe ſacred Books were not yet neer the time of their full Delivery, or it may be that a wiſe and experienced Midwife was wanting till now to help into the world the birth of this great miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry from holy Scripture; doubtleſs this noted pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction was reſerved for theſe happy and refined dayes; but may it pleaſe your good Holineſs to tell me who is that man, or rather who is that Angel that hath made this admirable diſcovery? It is replied, the <hi>Pope,</hi> a ſecular <hi>Prieſt</hi> named Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Patrick,</hi> who is Inveſted with a rich Abbey, worth five hundred pounds a year, ſcituate in <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundy,</hi> which I have granted unto him in conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the notable ſervices that he hath rendred unto me amongſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hereticks: he hath promis'd to proceed further, and is engaged by my liberallity to be mindfull of my Intereſt, and I am perſwaded that there is none ſo able to ſettle my Concerns in that Kingdom; for amongſt the Ladies I underſtand that he is in an high eſteem, becauſe of the excellency of his Naturall parts; he wants no Impudency to uſher him into every place, and to cauſe him to thruſt himſelf into every buſines, and his noſe into every matter. He can alſo make uſe of pious frauds, and Religious Cheats in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94068:5"/> an excellent manner, and with fair promiſes; gain many a good proſelite. I am certain there is never a famous &amp; a noted Curtiſan or Religious Votary in the Kingdom, but he hath by his ſubtilty drawn to me and my holy Church; Not to mention the multitudes of <hi>Iriſh</hi> whom he hath poſſeſt with a blind reſolution of obeying my Orders, nor the ſimple <hi>Engliſh,</hi> that he hath bewitcht with the vain hopes of future preferment, pleaſure, happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and his Ptieſtly favour; I muſt needs acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg that he is a moſt admirable man to manage my Concerns with Diſcretion; he is no leſs ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesful as appears by his late Initmation of brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to paſs the totall and entire converſion of men, able to byaſs all things for me in that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and to promote my long deſigned purpoſe: It is true he hath loſt ſomething of his good Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation amongſt the ſilly and preciſe <hi>Puritans,</hi> the fantaſtick <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> by being too free of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in a publick Baudy-houſe in <hi>Holland,</hi> and by viſiting thoſe of <hi>London</hi> too often, and more then I have allowed him: but this reputation he makes good, and raiſes again amongſt the better ſort of men, by helping them to a Whore in time of need; Theſe things I do approve of, I have granted the liberty of ſuch actions to all holy and Religious men of his Order, and to the reſt of my Clergy,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94068:5"/> Clergy, for I am of my predeceſſors good opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, let St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſay what he will, that the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate and pious Chriſtians as well as the men of the world muſt and do burn with the flames of Luſt, and Fornication, and may ſometimes taſt a little of the forbidden Fruit: I would rather have him do ſo, then commit Matrimony, becauſe by this meanes he is very gracious with the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerallity of brave Fellows of the Time, and he may by this proceeding be better able to do me ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; for men commonly love the Religion that approves and allows the fulfilling of our deſires; but when theſe little <hi>Piccadillos,</hi> Veniall Sins, acts of his humanity ſhould have diſgraced him, and his name amongſt the ſottiſh Vulgar that cannot un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand how that the things, that I permit and confirm by my example, become Vertuous when <hi>St: Peter</hi> whoſe Succeſſor I am ſhould have ſaid the contrary, and proclaimed them to be Vices. He hath done enough to deſerve our eſteem for ever, for he hath found the Maſſe in <hi>Holy Scripture.</hi> This diſcovery will do us a great deal of good, it will confirm our indulgence, approve of our grants of liberty to ſin; It will ſecure and fortifie our Monaſtrical Garriſons, and inſpire into our noble Monks an invincible courage; It will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat and deſtroy all the enemies of our State and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94068:6"/> Kingdom, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 15. In a word, I am in hopes that this new and ſeaſonable diſcovery will furniſh me with that by which I ſhall be able to maintain the Authority of <hi>St. Peter</hi>'s Keyes in the World, to enlarge my vaſt Dominions, to embelliſh the palaces of pleaſure where <hi>Peter</hi> took his delight, and where I have caus'd his name to be engraven as teſtimones that <hi>I</hi> have them from him to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe my Guards that are not neer ſo numerous as thoſe that did wait upon <hi>St. Peter</hi> when he went from place to place to publiſh the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel to maintain his Triple Crown that <note place="margin">In the Caſtle of <hi>St. Angelo</hi> and elſewhere <hi>St. Peter's</hi> Name is engra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</note> he hath left me in poſſeſſion. It is very well quoth the Cardinal if it be true; but I am in doubt whether it be ſo, and that when the diſcovery be examin'd, it will be found as vaine and groundleſs as your Temporall power upon thoſe words, <hi>here are two Swords,</hi> or your Holineſſes preeminency and Infallibility up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that other Text, <hi>It ſhall lead you into all truth,</hi> for your Holineſs knows as you did lately avow, that unleſs your poſſeſſion were ſtronger, and more aparant than your Right, you ſhould never obtaine what you now enjoy. Your Holineſs is obliged to the Ignorance of the Times, and the ſharpneſs of your Sword for your Dignity, Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94068:6"/> and Papal power, and not to any weak Text of holy Scripture. It is true anſwered the Pope, but this diſcovery is not to be doubted of, and Father <hi>Patrick</hi> hath convinced me by ſending to me a Bible turn'd into <hi>French</hi> by the Doctors of <hi>Lorrain</hi> printed at <hi>Paris</hi> 1664. for in the 3 <hi>ch. verſe</hi> 2. of <hi>Acts,</hi> theſe bleſſed words are to be read of the Apoſtles <hi>ſaying Maſs to the Lord;</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though this Tranſlation be in French, it is no leſs uſeful to <hi>England,</hi> for that Nation naturally loves, admires, and embraces whatſoever appears to them in a French garb and countenance let it be never ſo rediculous. It is eaſie to put the words into <hi>Engliſh</hi> as I underſtand Father <hi>Patrick</hi> hath already done, and confirmed it by the Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Jeſuites of <hi>Rheims,</hi> who have done ſomething more, for they have very well mingled their holy Gloſs with the obſcure Text of Scripture, ſo that we may with eaſe find in it all our Doctrines in expreſs words. Sure ſaith the Cardinal, this Father <hi>Patrick</hi> hath moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Spectacles of an admirable temper, ſeeing they have made him perceive things altogether Inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, for I have often read that paſſage, but I muſt needs confeſs my dulneſs, and the dimneſs of my ſight, and my Ignorance. I could never per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any ſuch thing, nor Imagine that the words
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94068:7"/> could be ſo Tranſlated, for I find in the Greek Text <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, where I have always Imagined that the Word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> did ſignifie to Miniſter, and ſerve: Now the ſervice and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry Intended is to be known only by the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the Diſcourſe; the Latine Tranſlations do thus render the words, <hi>Miniſtrantibus illis Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino,</hi> and the Verſion of <hi>Louvain</hi> in French, <hi>Eux ſervans en leur Miniſtere au Seigneur,</hi> that is, they ſerving in their Miniſtry to the Lord: the very Sequel of St. <hi>Lukes</hi> diſcourſe diſcovers what he means by this ſervice, and the Miniſtration, for he ſpeaks of certain perſons, amongſt whom were <hi>Barnabas,</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> that whiles they were, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, miniſtring unto the Lord, when they had Faſted, the Holy Ghoſt warned them to ſeparate from them <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> for the work unto which he had called them; therefore he adds, when they had faſted and prayed, they laid their hands upon them, and ſent them away; where the words <hi>when they had faſted and prayed,</hi> do ſufficiently diſcover the end and accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Miniſtration attributed unto theſe men. From whence we may eaſily conclude, that St. <hi>Luke</hi> underſtands by their prayer and faſting, acts of Devotion, the accompliſhmnt of what he had ſpoken of, when he tells of theſe perſons,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:94068:7"/> that they were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The Syrian Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation and the Arabick do diſcover the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts meaning, for they have rendred theſe words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, whilſt they were praying; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, we may conſider the quality and employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of theſe men concerned, St. <hi>Luke</hi> tells us that they were Prophets and Doctors; It is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be ſuppoſed that when he ſayes that they were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and Faſting, that they were employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about the Functions and Offices proper to their Callings; that is, they did miniſter unto the Lord by prophecying and teaching, and that afterwards they did Faſt and pray to obtain Gods bleſſing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Labours and Teaching. I am certain <hi>Cajetan</hi> favours this Interpretation, for he ſpeaks thus upon this Text: The nature of their ſervice and miniſtry is not here mentioned, but becauſe St. <hi>Luke</hi> names them Prophets and Deacons<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we are to underſtand that their Miniſtry was perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by teaching, and preaching. Untill this moment, may it pleaſe your Holineſs, I was of the opinion of <hi>Cajetan,</hi> that theſe words do repreſent the Apoſtles employed about the duties of their Function, and that they did miniſter to the Lord by teaching and preaching the word to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, by adminiſtring the Sacraments, and by other acts of piety and devotion. I beſeech your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94068:8"/> to make me underſtand more perfectly this diſcovery, and how this Reverend Prieſt hath found the Maſs in theſe words, and wherefore he hath given to them this Interpretation: I can't very well tell you replyed the Pope. I don't much trouble my ſelf to underſtand the Scripture, nor to ſeek into the Original Text: You know very well that theſe ſacred books have no better nor more Honourable place aſſigned them in our publick Aſſemblies, but my footſtool, for I am above all Holy Scripture; I muſt not therefore ſo much abaſe my ſelf and my dignity to pry and ſearch into it with too much curioſity, as if I were to depend only upon that: but Il' tell you as I conceive, how he comes to make this good Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery: He is by profeſſion one of my Prieſts, whoſe employment is daily to Tranſubſtantiate the Bread and the Wine into the Body and Blood of Chriſt. By degrees he is become ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Artiſt in the Miſtery of Tranſubſtantiation, that he hath found out an expedient how to Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiate alſo this and other paſſages of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture, and change the words <hi>Miniſtring unto the Lord,</hi> into theſe, ſaying <hi>Maſs unto the Lord.</hi> I am very well pleaſed with his Ingenuity, and no body muſt think this proceeding ſtrange, for if he hath the power to transform, and cauſe a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94068:8"/> metamorphoſis of ſolid ſubſtance, and turn Bread and Wine into other things of ſo great a diſparity as fleſh, bones, and blood; It is no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if Father <hi>Patrick,</hi> this Ingenious Prieſt, hath alſo transformed and changed one expreſſion into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if he can by his breath alone make the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Body of Chriſt now aſcended up into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, to be found in a few Crums of Bread, and a few drops of Wine. Why may not <hi>Patrick</hi> by the ſame art cauſe the Holy Maſs to be found al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in a paſſage of holy Scripture where it was never before. If he can ſo far command him who is named the <hi>Word</hi> to come down from Heaven, as often as he pleaſeth, he may with more eaſe obliege him to ſpeak what, and when he liſteth. In the Word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> he hath met with a motive that hath Incited him to this perform; this metamorphoſis for he hath met with certain happy Spirits of the Primitive World, who have Informed him that in the Council of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> this word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> was Interpreted by ſaying Maſs; therefore the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil furniſhes him with an excellent proof, upon which he depends much, becauſe in the Actr of this Council the Word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is Tranſlated by a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine. Author <hi>facere-miſſas,</hi> perform Maſſes as <hi>Juli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> tells us, who himſelf was of that Councill; And becauſe this word is ſo to be underſtood in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:94068:9"/> the deeds of this Council, therefore it hath the ſame ſignification by very good reaſon in the <hi>Acts</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles.</hi> Don't you think that this reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is right and good? I admire quoth the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal the ſubtilty of this Prieſt, but I am afraid that ſome damned Heretick will draw from this kind of reaſoning advantages againſt us, and as ſuch kind of people do already ſay, that we affirm of our Maſs, that it is not what it appears to be, that appears Bread, but that it is nothing leſs then Bread? ſo they will talk of this paſſage Tranſlated by Father <hi>Patrick,</hi> that it is not what it ſeems to be: That in appearance the Maſs is in the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation, but in the Original there is no ſhape of the Maſs to be ſeen. They will alſo ſay that the arguing from the Interpretation of the Word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> found in the Acts of the Counſel of <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon</hi> is not juſt, nor reaſonable, for a word may have a different ſignification in Ages ſo much at a diſtance from one another, for that Counſel was held 400 years after the Apoſtles: beſides theſe Hereticks may ſay, that the word <hi>Miſsa,</hi> Maſs, that was then lately found out, has ſince in this Age changed its ſignification; for it is with the Maſs as with men, their Faces differ before they come to an age of underſtanding, look upon a man in his Chilhood, and conſider him afterwards in his old
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:94068:9"/> Age, and you ſhall ſearce know him, ſo it is with this Name; If you look upon it in its firſt riſe, and afterwards take notice of it in the glorious appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that hath been given to it in theſe laſt Ages, and you will ſcarce believe them to be the ſame, you will find a ſtrange alteration: It may be ſaid of the Maſs as of <hi>Noahs</hi> Ark, and <hi>Theſeus</hi> Ship that it was the ſame, and yet not the ſame, for the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſyllables, and pronunciation is the ſame, but the uſe and ſignification is not the ſame; then it did ſignifie the diſmiſſion of the people, or the leave to depart out of the Congregation granted to the Catechumenes who were diſmiſt after Sermon, or to the Reſt of the Faithful ſent away after the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Sacraments at the end of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Service; Then they did ſay, <hi>Facere miſſum Catechumenis,</hi> or <hi>Facere miſſum fidelibus,</hi> that is to diſmiſs the Catechumenes, or the Faithful: this word did then ſignifie generally all the publick Service of God, at the end of which this diſmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was thus performed, <hi>Miſſa eſt.</hi> So that then they called the publick Prayers of the Church the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and preaching of the Word of God, and the adminiſtration of the Sacraments by the Name of Maſs; theſe things <hi>Bellarmin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> hath confeſt. Since the word is ſtrangely changed to ſignifie the holy Sacrament of the Altar which is, now its ordinary
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:94068:10"/> meaning, Some therefore may ſay, that in the Tranſlation of the Counſel of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> it was never employed in the meaning that Reveend Father <hi>Patrick</hi> em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployes it in the 3 <hi>chap.</hi> of the <hi>Acts;</hi> but doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs this excellent Abbot ſo well kill'd in Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutation can ſolve all the difficulties that may be made againſt him, and his Interpretation. But what benefit doth your Holineſs imagine that we receive from this bold attempt of Father <hi>Patrick?</hi> I conceive that he may have well encreaſed: the glory of the Maſs by raiſing it upon ſuch a noble Throne, and placing it to be ſeen upon the The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atre of Holy Scriptures. He doth alſo by this meanes diſcover its profound Antiquity, for it ſeems to be far more ancient than Chriſt and his holy Apoſtles, for he may eaſily prove by this Word, that all the Prieſts under the Law did ſay Maſs very reverendly as well as the Brieſts under <hi>Luke</hi> 1. 23. the Goſpel; for <hi>St. Luke</hi> tells us that <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chary</hi> had accompliſht <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which we muſt for the time to come Tranſlate, <hi>The dayes of his ſaying Maſs.</hi> And <hi>St Paul</hi> repreſents <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> ſprinking the blood upon <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb:</hi> 9. 21. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</note> which we muſt alſo render thus, <hi>All the Veſſels employed in ſaying Maſs.</hi> In the ſame place <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 11</note> the Apoſtle tells us that every Prieſt did
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:94068:10"/> daily <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is according to this good Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation <hi>Say Maſs:</hi> and elſewhere he diſcovers how Chriſt doth continually ſay Maſs in Heaven, for in the ſame Ep. to the <hi>Heb.</hi> he tells us, that <hi>we have an high Prieſt that is ſeated at the right hand of the throne of the Majeſty of God in Heaven,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that means <hi>ſaying Maſs in the Holy places.</hi> I conceive that the Holy Angels are Chriſts Deacons and Clarks in Heaven to anſwer him, becauſe in the ſame Epiſtle they are named <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: we are to underſtand by theſe words, <hi>Spirits that ſay Maſs.</hi> Your Holineſs that hath communication with Heaven may know ſomething more of theſe Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly matters: Well replyed the Pope, we have juſt cauſe to expect the ſpeedy converſion of all the Hereticks, and if Father <hi>Patrick</hi> hath boaſted of having made many a good Proſelyte, and turned them from proteſtantiſme to popery, although it was then but a Lye, he may have ſaid ſo by the ſpitit of prophecy, ſuch kind of deceits and falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods are to be conſidered and excuſed as ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pious frauds deſign'd to bring back to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the truth the poor deluded Hereticks; for my part I conceive that he did foreſee the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of all thoſe people that will now doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs embrace my Faith and profeſſion, for they have often promiſed to come to Maſs if we can but
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:94068:11"/> ſhew them the Maſs in Holy Scripture. Now they muſt of neceſſity acknowledg it to be there, mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger all their obſtinacy, we may therefore hope to ſee whole troops of men return again to the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom of my Holy Church. If after ſo clear a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vict on, and this undeniable diſcovery there be any ſo obſtinate as to ſhut their eyes, and refuſe to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg the Maſs, I will thunder againſt him from my <hi>Vatican,</hi> and ſend him to Hell before his time: For my part I find quoth the Cardinal that he hath much oblieged the Civil Magiſtrates and Princes in giving this meaning to the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for we muſt now look upon them as perſons who have liberty to ſay Maſs, for <hi>St. Paul</hi> names them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is according to this new ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, <hi>Singers, or bablers of Maſſes unto God</hi> Now I think of it, all our Roman Religion is mightily obliged to him, for he hath ſhewn us an expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent how to confirm all the Doctrines of our Holy Church without much difficulty, in placing them in expreſs words in Holy Scripture. We may now ſeek the paſſages that have any colour of ſuch Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, and Tranſlate them according to this good model of Father <hi>Patrick,</hi> for example Chriſt <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. 18. ſaid to St. <hi>Peter</hi> in the Goſpel, <hi>Thou art Peter, and upon this rock I will build my Church;</hi> there we maintain that Chriſt hath granted and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:94068:11"/> the Popes Authority upon <hi>Peter,</hi> and his Succeſſors. But becauſe theſe words are not ſo plain and clear for our purpoſe as we could well wiſh, why may not we make it plainer, and Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate it in expreſs words that may confute all the Hereticks in this manner, <hi>Thou art Pope, and upon this pope I will build my Church.</hi> Your Fancy quoth the Pope is very good, and makes much for our purpoſe. Doubtleſs all Chriſtendom admires the wit and piety of this Ingenious Father, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires that he may be well rewarded for his worth and cunning; we ſhall have our Court thronged with the Embaſſadors of ſeveral Princes to ſue for his promotion and reward; for my part I am al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready very much enclined to grant to Father <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trick</hi> my moſt ſpecial Favours, I do at preſent free him from the troubleſom Viſit of purgatory after his Deceaſe, and Decree that his Soul may leap directly into Heaven without ſtop or hindrance: We have granted this priviledge to many that are not ſo deſerving as this moſt Reverend Father, and it is but reaſon that he ſhould obtain this benefit from the Maſs, ſeeing that he hath been ſo great a Friend to her. We commonly ſay Maſs to free poor Souls from the flames of purgatory, and to draw them into a more temperate and more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant abode, why may not the Maſs from which he
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:94068:12"/> hath deſerv'd a good Reward hinder him from en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into this Incommodious burning? I will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo reward him in his life-time, I will enoble his pate with a Cardinals Cap, I conceive his head is bigg enough, and of a ſiſe able to bear this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with a <hi>bon meen:</hi> When his Holineſs had ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered theſe words, he began to bethink himſelf, and muſe upon what he had ſaid; well quoth he, rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing and ſhaking his head, there is ſomething comes into my mind that damps all my affections, for Father <hi>Patrick</hi> this ſubtle Wit that hath found the Maſs in Holy Writ, contrary to all appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, may alſo by chance find by his cunning and working fancy how to make Father <hi>Patrick</hi> a Pope, and by this means pull me out of my ſeat, and tumble me down of my Throne as an unlawfull Pope. This apprehenſion ſinks into my mind do what I can, and ſpoils all the affection that I had conceived for this Father, ſo that a ſmall matter might cauſe me to undertake his Deſtruction. As the Cardinal was opening his Lips to return an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; in ſteps a Gentleman of the popes Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber to acquaint his Holineſs that there were without a croud of perſons that did moſt paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately entreat for audience of his good Holineſs. When the pope had commanded them to come in; e found them to Be ſome of his Well-wiſher
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:94068:12"/> that came to advertiſe him of a great Tumult that had hapned in the <hi>Vatican</hi> Church between two comely Ladies; the one named her ſelf <hi>Vulgata Latim,</hi> the other was named Madam <hi>Franca Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio</hi> of the City of <hi>Louvain,</hi> two perſons of very good account; as they were at their Devotions they quarrell'd with that Fury, that they were ready to tear one another to pieces: Madam <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gata</hi> required the precedency, becauſe ſhe had been enobled by the Council of <hi>Trent;</hi> and could ſhew a very authentick patent for her Nobility; but Madam <hi>Franca Verſio</hi> could produce no ſuch An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, but pretended that ſhe was to have the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedency of the former; becauſe ſhe had been eno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, dignified, and bleſſed with a moſt Divine Berne a She-beauty, eſteemed and admired all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the World as a Goddeſs, ſhe being the only Mother that had bore in her Womb ſuch a Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtial production as the Goddeſs <hi>Miſſa:</hi> She reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not to yeild an ace to her Siſter Madam <hi>Vulga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Latina,</hi> but to diſpute the preeminency and the predency with her to the uttermoſt; and the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe ſhe was backt and aſſiſted by all her Countrymen, who did not much favour Madam <hi>Latina,</hi> becauſe they underſtood not her ſpeech. As ſoon as theſe perſons had repreſented the caſe to his Holineſs, the door being open, in ſteps an
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:94068:13"/> old Roman Lady my Lady <hi>Tradition,</hi> ſhe was at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired as the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> are repreſented in holy Scripture when they came to make peace with the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> at their entrance into the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Land; her Gown was old and moth-eaten, her ſhoes patcht with many old pieces, her face painted with many wrinkles, her food was dry bread, and mouldy bisket, all her Garments did beſpeak her to be but a durty, naſty, loathſom, and old <hi>Joane;</hi> nevertheleſs ſhe received the Reſpects of all the company at her entrance, becauſe ſhe did look with a grave countenance, and affect ſuch marks and liveries of Antiquity and Age, although ſhe was but young, and of a late Birth, ſhe acceſſed his Holineſs without any Ceremony, becauſe ſhe was very well known to him, and familiar with him, ſhe had tutered him, and did yet furniſh him with very good directions. This Lady <hi>Tradition</hi> with a grim and ſad countenance ſoon burſt forth into bitter complaints againſt Father <hi>Patrick</hi> the <hi>French Abbot,</hi> and the <hi>Iriſh Prieſt</hi> for having com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted a moſt unjuſt robbery and rape, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baucht and carried away from her dwelling one of her beſt and moſt beautiful Gueſts my Lady <hi>Miſſa:</hi> ſhe repreſented to his Holineſs that he had juſt cauſe to fear further Injuries and wrongs from this Father, and that ſhe was afraid leſt he ſhould
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:94068:13"/> alſo debauch her other Gueſts, and perſwade them to leave her deſolate, and by that means take away all her livelihood and being for without them ſhe is not able to ſubſiſt. As ſhe was opening the Caſe, and accuſing of Father <hi>Patrick,</hi> all her Gueſts or Lodgers came into the Room together to make alſo their ſeveral complaints, and aſſiſt their old Landlady in her accuſation. The Marqueſs of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory with all his Attendants went formoſt The Count <hi>Meritum,</hi> and Viſcount <hi>Free will</hi> with a long Train of Followers, fill'd the Room where his Holineſs was. Theſe Noble Perſons that I have named are all Officers of our mother the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> The Marqueſs of Purgatory is the great Purveyor and principal Cook, to him it belongs to ſee that the Pot may boil well, Count <hi>Meritum</hi> is the great Treaſurer of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church; for he hath in his cuſtody all the Riches and Treaſures by which he intends to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe the Kingdom of Heaven. Viſcount <hi>Free-will</hi> is the <hi>Fac-totum,</hi> or Governour of the Houſe, he is the Porter or Uſher to introduce or ſhut out whom he pleaſeth. He is alſo the Steward &amp; Controller of the mother Church for he diſpoſeth of all at his pleaſure. He is a capricious and humerſome Knave; never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs the Catholick Church i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> very well pleaſed with his ſervices, and cannot be perſwaded to leave
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:94068:14"/> him. Aſſoon as my Lord Marqueſs of Purgatory appeared, every mothers ſon in the Room began to tremble for fear; for he was cloathed with a fiery Garb moſt terrible to the eye, out of his mouth burſt forth flaſhes of extraordinary fire, ſo that every one made room to him, and was afraid to come near him; but when the ſpectators had well view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, they perceived that his terrible Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance had nothing of reality, and that this fire, and the ſeeming flames were the effects only of their deluded imagination My Lord; merit was clad in ſuch a Garb, and appeared with ſuch a pleaſant mean, that he was more able to move laughter than fear, for he ſeemed to be proud and high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded: His Countenance, Behaviour and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage was much like that of a <hi>French</hi> Coxcomb, or of a proud and ſtately <hi>Spaniard.</hi> He did blow and puff as a man out of breath, and with Eyes full of contempt he did ſpeak to every one; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65. 1. <hi>Come not near me for I am more holy than thou:</hi> In his hand he held a large Purſe full of good Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters with which men do commonly reckon with God Almighty to ſee how much he is in their debt. My Lord, Free-will appeared in another Attire; and Behaviour, not ſo ridiculous, but no leſs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant; for his inconſtancy and unſetled Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage did make him appear very ſimple; for he ſtood
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:94068:14"/> now upon one ley then upon another. He had got a <hi>Switzers</hi> Garbe and Attire, of ſeveral Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, to expreſs the diverſity and variableneſs of our Free-will, but that which was moſt remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in his appearance was, that he had got a Stee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple upon his head that did bear a Croſs, with a VVether-cock on the top, to repreſent how that in the buſineſs of our Salvation ſignified by the Croſs. It was in his power to turn himſelf any ways. At firſt all theſe Noble Lords were ready to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a cruel diſpute, and quarrel, becauſe they all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to the priviledge of ſpeaking firſt, my Lord Marqueſs had a large &amp; wide mouth, as great as that of an Oven, and much heat to animate his diſcourſe; and therefore a greater advantage to ſpeak firſt, than the reſt: my Lord, merit did produce his worth and excellency; and therefore that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to be the ſpokeſman, my Lord Free-will alledged, that merit was indebted to him for the advantages by which he pretended to the priviledge of ſpeaking firſt; for there could be no merit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Free-will. To pleaſe 'um all, the Pope com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded 'um to ſpeak all together, and told 'um that he was well able to underſtand all their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes together: That although he appeared but with one Head, he had got one that was worth many, for it was able to bear three Crowns, That
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:94068:15"/> it were to do him wrong to fancy that he had leſs ability than the Beaſt of the Revelations that had Seven Heads, and therefore could underſtand the Speeches of ſeven perſons: And that as he was the Head of the Church, he muſt needs have this power of an Head to underſtand the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, and feel the griefs of ſeveral members at once when they endure pain, when the Pope had granted to them this permiſſion, and leave to ſpeak all at once, every one began to declare their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints to this effect: That Father <hi>Patrick</hi> had done them all the greateſt injury that could be, by divorcing and carrying away the Maſs their dear Companion from them: That they had long lodged together peaceably, with much unity and love, at the Palace of my Noble Lady, my Lady <hi>Traditio:</hi> That to part with their Companion, they could as well part with Heart and Soul and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that they did reckon that Father <hi>Patrick</hi> had done them a notable prejudice to place the Maſs in Holy Scripture without them: That they had as good reaſon to pretend to that Honour as well as ſhe, for there be ſome places of Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture that favour as much their being, as that place doth the Maſs. The Marques of Purgatory al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd a paſſage of the firſt of <hi>Corinthians,</hi> where theſe words are to be found, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 15. <hi>VVh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are ſaved as by fice,</hi> why ſaid he may not one add to the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:94068:15"/> tranſlantion, by the fire of Purgatory. <hi>Meritum</hi> brought forth a paſſage of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> where the perſons are mentioned, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. 4. <hi>VVhom God will cauſe to walk in white Cloathing, becauſe they are worthy.</hi> He deſired that one might render the words, becauſe they do merit it. My Lord <hi>Free will</hi> fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied that the paſſage of <hi>Denteronomy</hi> made for him, where God told the Children of <hi>Iſrael, Deut.</hi> 36. 40. <hi>That tbe VVord was near them in their mouth, and in their Heart to do it:</hi> vvherefore ſaid he may not vve tranſlate it, is in thy Free-vvill to do it: Therefore every one of them did conclude that his Holineſs muſt needs, if he will deal impartially, do of two things one, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſtore the Maſs to its old Lodging, and former Camerades, or grant to them to dwell with her un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame Roof In the heat of the diſpute they fell from reaſons to threatnings againſt his Holineſs in caſe that they did not receive due ſatisfaction; for the Marques of Purgatory threatned to be even with his Holineſs when his Soul ſhould enter into his Dominions, if he did not grant his deſire and do Juſtice; for he that frees others by his authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty from burning in Purgatory, cannot exempt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from thoſe Torments. Therefore he threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to caſt ſo much Brimſtone, and combuſtible matter into the ſcorching Flames, that he would increaſe the heat in ſuch a manner, that he ſhould
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:94068:16"/> have firſt cauſe to repent. <hi>Meritum</hi> threatned him, that if he did not do as he deſired, that he would for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake his perſon: So that without his aſſiſtance, he ſhould be without means of ever arriving to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, or entring into that place of bliſs. My Lord, Free-wil freely declared to him, that unleſs he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained his Requeſt, he ſhould fall into ſuch fits of Melancholy, that he would leave the humane So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety: So that they might by that means, become <hi>Janſeniſts,</hi> that are near related the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> the Popes ſworn Enemies. This laſt threatning did not much trouble his Holineſs, becauſe he knew that the Viſcounts Pate was full of Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilver and Whimſey, therefore never ſetled in its reſolutions. He knew alſo that he would never do any thing in favour of the <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> becauſe they are an envious Generation of men, that won't allow him his Titles of Honour, but have often at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to cut off his Head, and when they could not perform that, they have reduced and condemed him to ſlavery &amp; perpetual bondage; but the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of the reſt terrified the poor Pope. As he was thinking what was beſt to be done, he hears a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Bell coming in, and my Lady <hi>Maſs</hi> in perſon followed immediately after. This dainty Dame that never goes a foot, nor treads upon the ſlimy ground, was carryed by a Cardinal Prieſt. She can
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:94068:16"/> ride very well on Horſeback, for in the ſolemn proceſſions at <hi>Rome</hi> ſhe is commonly moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon a white Horſe; but in this occaſion ſhe could not make uſe of ſuch a carriage, for ſhe was forced to come up ſtaires to the Pope; when all the Aſſiſtants beheld my Lady <hi>Maſs,</hi> they wondered wherefore ſhe was come, they began to look one upon another, to ſee which of the company was ſo ſick as to need my Lady to comfort him: the Prieſt that carried her ſoon ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied them by addreſſing himſelf to the Pope in my Ladies name in this manner; Great Vicar, and Lieutenant of God, viſible Head of the Univerſal Catholick Church, moſt powerful God on Earth, I come to demand Juſtice of the Inſolency, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudency, and temerity of Father <hi>Patrick,</hi> who hath baſely raviſht, and againſt my will carried me away by plaine force from my houſe and home, to cauſe me to dwell in a ſtrange place. I was very well ſatisfied in my old Lodgings in my Lady <hi>Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o's</hi> place; nothing was there wanting to my per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or dignity, for my Lady is very well provided with all neceſſaries, and is moſt complizant to all her Gueſts. I confeſs that <hi>Holy Scripture</hi> is an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable dwelling indeed; but this Fellow hath appointed me there ſuch an Incommodious Abode that I proteſt I can ſtay there no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:94068:17"/> I am confined to this narrow Leaſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, where I am ſo ill accomodated, that I am in danger to fall down at every moment, whereas before I was ſeated upon a Throne at my pleaſure, where I had elbow-room enough. This Block-head has imagined that I ſhould be here better plac'd, and better able to convince all Hereticks, whereas it is here that I am meekeſt, and not able ſo much as to defend my ſelf. I may ſay as <hi>David,</hi> when he took upon him <hi>Sauls</hi> Armor to encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with <hi>Goliah,</hi> I can't walk with all this, for I am not uſed to 'um. Thus I may ſay, that it is altogether Impoſſible that I ſhould make uſe of this paſſage to overcome the Hereticks, becauſe I am not uſed to it: Beſides, as I am there plac'd without Gods approbation, and contrary to all reaſon, and ſince I am therefore there againſt my will, and have as much reaſon to complain as <hi>Abſalom</hi> when he was brought from <hi>Geſsur</hi> to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> where he had not the liberty to ſee King <hi>David, Wherefore am I come from Geſſur? it was better for me to remain there ſtill.</hi> Moreover, he hath put me there all naked, without my orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, without my <hi>Alba</hi> Girdle, <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ola</hi> Cope, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſuch-like Veſtments that became my dignity, whereas I had all this attire in my former habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: All ſuch as ſhall ſee me here, will imagine
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:94068:17"/> that I have a great delight to make my abode wherever the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is to be found, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they will imagine ſuch things as become not my quality and grandeur; for example when St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes to the <hi>Phillipians, ch.</hi> 2. <hi>V.</hi> 30. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, they will Infer from thence, <hi>That I am to be delivered, and offered up by the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure hands of Laymen, as well as by the holy Prieſts.</hi> Thus when St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith to the <hi>Romans,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Some may think that I am re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd and rankt amongſt impure and carnal things ſuch as are given by men in Almes: This fellow hath alſo lodged me at a ſtrange houſe and dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling without the leave of the Landlords and own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; for he hath plac'd me in the Tranſlation of the Doctors of <hi>Louvain,</hi> who never thought to place me there, for they have Tranſlated this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage into words that don't diſcover any ſhadow of the Maſs. I have alſo reaſon to complain that I am there lodg'd in an unworthy manner, for he makes me paſſe but for a Diſcourſe, whereas I am in truth a glorious Sacrifice offered to God for the benefit of the quick and the dead, for he repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents me in theſe words, <hi>They ſaying Maſs unto the Lord,</hi> wheras he ſhould have ſaid, <hi>They offering Maſs up to the Lord;</hi> for theſe reaſons I am become a ſcorn to the Hereticks, and a reproach and ſhame to the good Catholicks. At <hi>Paris</hi> Reverend Doctors of the <hi>Sorbonne</hi> do in no wiſe approve of this bold at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:94068:18"/> and will ſcarce take notice of me in this corner; I do therefore deſire that by your Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity you will take me from this place, and lodge me where I was wont before. And I did deſire that you would inflict upon this Impudent Prieſt the puniſhment that his audacity deſerves. When my Lady <hi>Maſs</hi> had ended her Speech, the Pope that had been diſ-ſatisfied with <hi>Patricks</hi> proceedings, ſoon granted the Requeſts of all the Aſſiſtants: Therefore he returned this anſwer to my Lady <hi>Miſſa,</hi> Great and Admirable Sacrament of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, Divine Maſs, I grant that thou ſhouldeſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to thy former Abode; And I further Decree, that Father <hi>Patrick</hi> ſhall make thee all juſt amends and ſatisfaction for thy diſgrace. I do alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare him to have forfeited his Offices and privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, and that he is become unworthy ever to ſay Maſs again, or to enjoy any Eccleſiaſtical Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; I do therefore enjoyn him as a Penance, that he ſhal Whip his Bomfiddle twice every day, that he ſhall never drink any thing but Water whilſt he lives, but not to reduce him to utter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair; I leave to his choice to take Holy, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Water at his pleaſure; and I allow him to make uſe of an Whore when he hath occaſion.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Reader,</salute> Take heed of the Hypocriſie and Cunning of the Romiſh Emiſſaries. VALE.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:94068:18"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 2. Line 2. for naked read noted, p. 4. l. 13. r. Intimation, p. 5. l. 25. r. - Monaſtical, p. 7. l. 6. r. <hi>Lovvain,</hi> p. 11. l. 17. blot out this and; p. 23. r. Acts p. 16. l. 2. r. Maugre, p. 18. l. laſt r. he, p. 19 l. 4. r. Latin, p. 22. l. 13. r, Meene, p. 23. l. 1. r. Leg.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
